<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discouerie of the treasons practised and attempted against the Queenes Maiestie and the realme, by Francis Throckmorton who was for the same arraigned and condemned in Guyld Hall, in the citie of London, the one and twentie day of May last past.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24050.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19952693</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19952693</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23559</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13753)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 334:5 or 1717:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discouerie of the treasons practised and attempted against the Queenes Maiestie and the realme, by Francis Throckmorton who was for the same arraigned and condemned in Guyld Hall, in the citie of London, the one and twentie day of May last past.</title>
                  <author>Q. Z.</author>
                  <author>Throckmorton, Francis, 1554-1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>C. Barker],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: A true and perfect declaration of the treasons practised and attempted by Francis Throckemorton.</note>
                  <note>Includes two letters, one written by Q.Z. and one by Throckmorton.</note>
                  <note>Place and name of publisher suggested by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]² A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24050 at reel 334:5.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (reel 334) and Bodleian Library (reel 1717).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Throckmorton, Francis, 1554-1584.</term>
               <term>Treason --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23559:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A diſcouerie of the treaſons practiſed and attempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Queenes Maieſtie and the Realme, by <hi>Francis Throckmorton,</hi> who was for the ſame arraigned and condemned in Guyld Hall, in the Citie of London, the one and twentie day of May laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23559:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23559:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is in this ſhort diſcourſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto thee (gentle reader) a true report of the treaſons and practiſes of <hi>Francis Throckmorton,</hi> &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plices againſt the Queenes Maieſtie and the Realme: which comming to my handes by chance from a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, to whom it was ſent into the Countrey, I haue preſumed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the ſame to the print, to the ende that ſuch as in opinion and conceite are not ſatisfied, touching the matters proued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and the courſe of proceeding helde with him, might by the ſight thereof (if trueth and reaſon may perſwade them) bee reſolued of all ſuch doubtes and ſcruple as haue riſen by the variable reportes made of the qualitie of his offences, and the maner of dealing vſed towards him: for the better knowledge whereof, I referre thee to the declaration fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and ſo commit thee to God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:23559:3"/>
            <head>A letter ſent from a gentleman of Lions Inne to his friend, concerning <hi>Francis Throckmorton,</hi> who was arraigned and condemned of high Treaſon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Yr, with my laſt letters of the firſt of Iune, I ſent vnto you in writing the arraigneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Francis Throckmorton</hi> penned by a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of good skill and credite, being preſent at the ſame and becauſe it hath ſeemed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me that there is ſome ſcruple in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite touching the ſufficiencie of the euidece produced againſt him, I haue for your better ſatisfaction endeuoured to attaine to more particular knowledge thereof, and by the meanes of a ſecret friend, there is come vnto my hands, a verſe perfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, of the whole proceedings helde by ſuch as were in commiſſion for the examining of him before his triall coutal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the materiall pointes of the treaſons by him confeſſed, where unto there is annexed a ſubmiſſion written by <hi>Francis Throckmorton</hi> to the Queenes Maieſtie, the fourth of Iune, whereby he acknowledgeth that he hath vntruely and vnduetifully denied his former confeſſions, &amp; vnder his hand writing hath eftſoones repeated and confeſſed the ſame confeſſions to be true (ſome fewe things onely detracted, but of no moment:) which may in mine opinion remooue all matter of doubt or ſcruple conceiued by you or by any other of his iuſt condemnation. You know howe well I haue alwayes loued the man, and delighted to conuerſe with him in reſpect of the good partes wherewith he was indued, and of the pleaſant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour that for the moſt part did poſſeſſe him when hee came in companie of friendes, yeelding at no time (to my ſeeing) any ſhew or ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue bene a dealer in matters of that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litte: &amp; therefore I cannot but pitie his miſfortune the more, wiſhing all men to make profite of his fal, and to note, that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and calamitie of this kinde, doeth for the moſt part fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſuch as forget God, to whoſe protection I committe you. From Lyons Inne, the 15 of Iune. 1584.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured friend. Q.Z.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:23559:3"/>
            <head>A true and perfect declaration of the Treaſons practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and attempted by Francis Throcke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morton, late of London, againſt the Queenes Maieſtie and the Reaime.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas there haue bene very lewde and ſlaunderous bruites and reportes giuen out, of the due and orderly proceedings held with <hi>Francis Throckmorton</hi> lately anaigned and condenmed of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the Guildhall in London the xxi. day of May laſt, whereby ſuch as are euill affected toward her Maleſtie, and the preſent gonernement, haue inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed falſely and iniuriouſly to charge her Maieſtie and her faithfull miniſters with crueltie and iniuſtice uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>Throckemerton</hi> by extorting from him by torture, ſuch confeſſions as he hathmade againſt himſelfe, and by inſorcing the ſame to make thom lawful euidence to conflict him of the treaſons therein ſpecified. Albeit her Maieſties ſubieuts in general walling to minde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> milde and temperace courſe ſhe hath helde all the time of her moſt happie Reigne, might rather impute her clemencie and lenitie vſed to wards all fortes of offenders to a kinde of fault, then taxe her in the contrarie: yet ſuch as allowe of practiſe and treaſons againſt her Maieſtie, de awayes interpaexe both of the one and of the other, according to the partiouias affections that docopoſſeſſe them, that is, to the worſt. And foraſmuch as the caſe of <hi>Throckemorton</hi> at this time hath bene ſubiect to their ſiniſter conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conſidering that lies and falſe bruites caſt abroad are moſt commonly beleeuch until they be ontroſſed by
<pb facs="tcp:23559:4"/>the trueth: it hath bene thought expedient in this ſhort diſcourſe to deliuer vnto your view and conſideration, a true and perfect declaration of the treaſons practiſed and attempted by the ſaid <hi>Throckemorton</hi> againſt her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie &amp; the Realme, by him confeſſed before his arraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby her Maieſtie was iuſtly and in reaſon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to put him to his triall. You ſhall likewiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what courſe hath bene helde with him by her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to bring him to confeſſe the trueth: with what impudencie and how falſely he hath denied his ſayings and confeſſions: And laſtly, how by a new ſubmiſſion and confeſſion of his ſaid treaſons ſithens his condemnation, he endeuoureth to ſatiſſie her Maieſtie, and to ſhew the reaſons thea mooued him to denie the firſt, which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth and confirmeth by the laſt: which may in reaſon ſatiſfie, though not all, yet ſuch as are not foreſtalled, or rather forepoyſoned and infected with the lies and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes alreadie ſpred and deliuered, in fauour of the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and his treaſons. You ſhall therefore vnderſtand, that the cauſe of his apprehenſion grewe firſt vpon ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence giuen to the Queenes Maieſtie, that he was a priuie conueiour and receiuour of letters to and from the Scottiſh Queene, vpon which information neuertheleſſe diuers moneths were ſuffered to paſſe on, before he was called to anſwere the matter, to the end there might ſome proofe more apparant be had to charge him there with directly: which ſhortly after fell out, and thereupon there wereſent vnto his houſes in London, and at Leuſham in Kent to ſearch and apprehoud him, certaine gentlemen of no me anc credice and reputation of whom, two were ſent to his houſe by Poules wharfe, where he was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and ſo by one of them conuayed preſemly away, the other remaining in the chamber to make ſearch for papers, writings, &amp;c. which might giue proofe of his fuſpected practiſes.</p>
            <p>In that ſearth, there were found the two papers contar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:23559:4"/>the names of certaine Catholique Noblemen and gentlemen, expreſſing the Hauens for landing of forraine forces, with other particularities in the ſaid papers men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, the one written in the Secretarie hand, (which he at the Barre confeſſed to be his owne hand writing) and the other in the Romane hand, which he denied to be his, and would not ſhewe how the ſame came vnto his hands: howbeit in his examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s he hath confeſſed them both to be his owne hand writing, and ſo they are in trueth. There were alſo found among other of his papers, twelue petidegrees of the diſcent of the Crowne of England, printed and publiſhed by the Blſhop of Roſſe, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the pretended title of the Scottiſh Queene his Miſtreſſe, with certaine infamous libelles againſt her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie printed &amp; publiſhed beyond the ſeas: which being found in the hands of a man ſo cuill affected, comparing the ſame with his doings and practiſes againſt her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, you wil iudge the purpoſe wherefore he kept them.</p>
            <p>Shortly after his apprehenſion, hee was examined by ſome of her Maieſties priuie counſell, how he came by the ſaid two papers of the Hauens, and he moſt impudently denied with many proteſtations that he neuer ſawe them, affirming they were none of his, but were foiſted in (as he termed it) among his papers by the gentlemen that ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his houſe: Notwithſtanding being more earneſtly preſſed to confeſſe the trueth, he ſayd they had bene left (he knew not how) in his chamber by a man of his, who not long before was departed out of the Realme, named <hi>Edward Rogers, alias Nuttebie,</hi> by whome they were written. And to make this deuice to carie ſome colour of trueth, after his committing to the Tower, hee found the meanes to get three Cardes, on the backeſide of which Cardes he wrote to his brother <hi>George Throck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merton</hi> to this effect: <hi>I haue bene examined by whom the two papers, conteining the names of certaine Noblemen and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and of Hauens &amp;c. were written: and I haue allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:23559:5"/>them to haue bene written by Edward Nutteby my man, of whoſe hand writing you knowe them to be:</hi> Meaning by this deuice to haue had his brother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme his falſehode. Theſe Cardes were intercepted, and thereby the ſuſpition before conceiued of his practiſes increaſed, whereupon, as vpon other iuſt cauſe and matter againſt him, hauing bin ſundrie tunes brought before ſome of the principall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages of her Maieſties moſt honorable priuie counſell, and by them with all induſtrie examined, and perſwaded in very milde and charitable maner, to confeſſe the trueth, promiſing to procure pardon for him, in caſe he woulde bewray the depth of his practiſes: but no perſuaſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing, her Maieſtie thought it agreeable with good pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, and the ſafetie of her Royal perſon and ſtate, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him ouer to the hands of ſome of her learned counſel and others her faithfull ſeruants and miniſters, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to them, to aſſay by torture to drawe from him the trueth of the matters appearing ſo waightie as to concerne the inuading of the Realme, &amp;c. Theſe men by vertue of that commiſſion, proceeded with him, firſt as the counſell had formerly done by way of perſuaſion, to induce him to confeſſe: but finding that courſe not to preuaile, they were conſtrained to commit him to ſuch as are vſually appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Towre to handle the Racke, by whom he was layd vpon the ſame, and ſomewhat pinched, although not much: for at the end of three daies following, he had recouered himſelfe, and was in as good plight as before the time of his racking, which if it had then or any other time bene miniſtred vnto him with that violence that hee and his fauourers haue indeuoured ſlaunderouſly to giue out, the ſignes thereof would haue appeared vpon his limmes for manie yeeres. At this firſt time of torture, hee would confeſſe nothing, but continued in his former ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie and deniall of the trueth. The ſecond time that bee was put to the Racke, before hee was ſtrayned vp to any purpoſe, hee yeelded to confeſſe any thing
<pb facs="tcp:23559:5"/>hee knewe, in the matters obiected againſt him: whereupon he was looſed, and then the Commiſſioners proceeded with him according to ſuch Interrogatories as had bene deliuered vnto them, which for the more breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall here bee omitted, the intent of this declaration, tending onely to diſcouer vnto you the treaſons and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous dealings of the ſaid <hi>Francis Throckamorton</hi> aſwell before as ſithens his impriſonment, for your better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the man, and manifeſtation of the due and iuſt proceedings held with him by her Maieſties Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners appointed to that ſeruice. And here you are to note, that when hee was firſt preſſed to diſcouer by whome the plottes of the Hauens were ſette downe, and to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he began (without any further interrogation mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred) by way of an hiſtoricall narration, to declare that at his being at Spaw in the Countrie of <hi>Liege</hi> certaine yeres paſt, he entred into conference with one Ienney a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous knowen Traitor, touching the altering of the ſtate of the Realme here, &amp; how the ſame might be attempted by forraine inuaſion, and to the like effect bad ſundrie confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences with <hi>Sir Francis Englefield</hi> in the low Countreys, who daily ſolicited the Spaniſh king in Spaine, &amp; his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours in the ſaid Countreyes, to attempt the inuading of the Realme, continued a courſe of practiſing againſt her Maieſtie and the ſtate, by letters betweene <hi>Sir Francis Englefielde</hi> and himſelfe, vntill within theſe two yeres laſt paſt, and that he did from time to time acquaint <hi>Sir Iohn Throckemorton</hi> his late father with his traiterous practiſes, who (as he ſaid) ſeeing no probabilitie of ſucoeſſe in them, diſſuaded himfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any further medling w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe practiſes.</p>
            <p>He hath further confeſſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he vſed his Fathers aduiſe &amp; opinion in ſetting downe the names of the Catholique Noblemen and Gentlemen, and did acquaint him with the deſcription of the Hauens for the landing of forces, which he conceiued and put in writing onely by view of the Mappe, and not by particular ſight or ſuruey of the
<pb facs="tcp:23559:6"/>ſaid Hauens.</p>
            <p>Item, he hath alſo confeſſed, that vpon the intermiſsion of writing of letters, and the accuſtomed intelligences paſſed betweene <hi>Sir Francis Englefield</hi> and him, he was made acquainted by his brother <hi>Thomas Throckemorton,</hi> by letters &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, and by <hi>Thomas Morgan</hi> by letters (two o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>f the principall confederates and workers of theſe treaſons reſlding in France) with a reſolute determination agreed on by the Scottiſh Queene and her confederats in France and in other forreine partes, and alſo in Englande, for the inuading of the Realme.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Duke of Guyſe</hi> ſhould be the principal leader and executer of that inuaſion.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>pretention</hi> (which ſhoulde be publiquely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified) ſhould be to deliuer the Scottiſh Queene to libertie, and to procure euen by force from the Queenes Maieſtie, a tolerance in religion for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pretended Catholiques: But the <hi>intention,</hi> (the bottome whereof ſhould not at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt be made knowen to all men) ſhoulde be vpon the Queenes Maieſties reſiſtance, to remooue her Maieſtie from her Crowne and ſtate.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Duke of Guyſe</hi> had prepared the forces, but there wanted two things, money, and the aſsiſtance of a conuenient partie in England, to ioyne with the forraine forces, and a third thing, how to ſet the Scottiſh Queene at libertie without perill of her perſon.</p>
            <p>For, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt thing wanting, <hi>viz.</hi> money, meſſengers were ſent from forraine parts both to Rome &amp; Spaine, &amp; their returne daily expected to their liking: And the Spaniſh Ambaſſador to encourage the Engliſh to ioyne both in purſe and perſon, did gine out, that the King his Maſter woulde not onely make ſome notable attempt againſt Englande, but alſo woulde beare halfe the charge of the enterpriſe. For the ſeconde thing, <hi>viz.</hi> the preparing of a ſufficient partie in England, to receiue and to ioyne with the forraine forces, one eſpeciall meſſenger was ſent ouer
<pb facs="tcp:23559:6"/>into England in Auguſt laſt, vnder a counterſaite name from the confederates in France, to ſignifie the platte and preparation there, and to ſollicite the ſame here.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Thomas Throckemerton</hi> his brother made him priuie to his negotiation at his laſt being here in England, and that thereupon <hi>Frauncis Throckmerton</hi> tooke vpon him to be a follower and meane for the effectuating ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of among the confederats in Englande with the holpe of the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour, whom he inſtructed howe and with whome to deale for the preparing of a conuenient partie heere within the Realme, for that himſelfe woulde not be ſeene to be a ſounder of men, leſt hee might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and ſo endanger himſelfe &amp; the enterpriſe, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Ambaſſadour being a publique perſon, might ſafelie deale therein without perill.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Duke of Guyſe</hi> and other heads of the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe had refuſed ſome landing places, and made ſpeciall choiſe of Suſſex, and about Arundel in Suſſex, both for the neere cutte from the parts of Fraunce, where the <hi>Duke</hi> did or beſt could aſſemble his force, and for the oportunitie of aſſured perſons to giue aſſiſtance, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That hee, taking vpon him the purſuite of this courſe, ſhewed the whole plotte and deuiſe of the hauens for lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Spaniſh Ambaſſador, who did incourage him therein, he promiſing, that if hee might haue reſpite vntill the next ſpring, the ſame ſhould be done more exactly.</p>
            <p>That at the time of <hi>Thomas Throckemertons</hi> being here, leaſt the negotiation of the enterpriſe, by ſome caſualtie might faile in the only hand of one man <hi>Thomas Throck, morton,</hi> there was alſo from the confederats ſent ouer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Suſſex, <hi>Charles Paget,</hi> vnder the name of <hi>Mope, alias Spring,</hi> and therof an aduertiſement couettly ſent to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Throckmorten,</hi> both that Thomas might vnderſtande it, and not be offended that another was ioyned with him in his labour.</p>
            <p>That the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour by aduertiſements from
<pb facs="tcp:23559:7"/>the confederates, was made priuie to this comming of <hi>Charles Paget</hi> vnder the name of <hi>Mope,</hi> and yet knowen to him to be <hi>Charles Paget.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the ſaid Ambaſſadour did according to his ſayde aduertiſements, knowe and affirme that <hi>Charles Paget</hi> was come ouer to view the hauens and Countrey for lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch forraine forces about Arundell, and ſpecially to ſound and conferre with certaine prineipall perſons for aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The ſame Ambaſſadour alſo knewe and affirmed, that <hi>Charles Paget</hi> had accordingly done his meſſage, and had ſpoken with ſome principall perſons heere, according to his commiſſion, and was returned.</p>
            <p>Hee moreouer confeſſed that there was a deuice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour and him, howe ſuch principall Recuſants here within the Realme as were in the Commiſlion of the peace in ſundrie Counties, might vpon the firſt bruite of the landing of forrame forces, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour and pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt of their authoritie and the defence of her Maieſtie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men, whome they might after ioyne to the forraine forces, and conuert them againſt her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
            <p>In theſe fewe articles is briefly compriſed the whole ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his confeſſio made at large without any Intert oga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie particularly miniſtred, other then vpon that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers before mencioned, contayning the names of men o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hauens. And heere you are to note that at the time of his apprehenſion, there was no knowledge or doubt had of theſe treaſons, or of his priurtie vnto the in, but onely an information and ſo pition deliuered &amp; conceiued of ſome practeſe betweene him and the Scottily Queene as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned. For the diſcouering whereof, after he had bene ſundrie times vpon his alleagaunce commended to declare his doings in conueying and receyuing of letters to and from her, he did voluntarily confeſſe that hee had written diuers letters vnto her, and had conueyed many
<pb facs="tcp:23559:7"/>to and fro, betweene her &amp; <hi>Thomas Morgan</hi> in France, by whoſe meanes he was firſt made knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto her, &amp; that he had receiued as many letters from her. Hee alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the effect of his letters to her, &amp; of hers to him: which letters betwene them were alwaies written in Cipher, and the Cipher with the Nullities and markes for names of Princes and Counſailors, hee ſent vnto the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie written with his owne hand, Hee alſo deliuered the names of ſome, by whom hee conueyed his letters to the Scottiſh Queene, as by one <hi>Godfrey Fulgeam,</hi> who fled the Realme immediatly vpon <hi>Throckemortons</hi> apprehenſion, and one other perſon, whom he deſcribed by his ſtature, ſhape, and apparell, and the man ſithens apprehended and examined, hath confeſſed the ſame: the mans name is <hi>William Ardington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſumme and effect of the moſt part of theſe confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, although they were at the time of his arraignement opened and dilated by her Maieſties Sergeant, Atturney, and Sollicitor generall at the barre, and therefore ſeeme not needfull to be repeated heere, yet becauſe the purpoſe of this diſcourſe is to ſhew ſufficient proofe, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters contained in his ſaid confeſſions, are neither falſe nor fayned (as <hi>Frauncis Throckmorton</hi> moſt impudently affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at his triall, alleadging that they were meere inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of him ſelfe by policie to auoyde the torture) they haue bene here inſerted, to the ende you may the better iudge of the proofes, preſumptions, and circumſtances folowing, by comparing the matters with their accidents, and conſequently ſee the falſehoode of the Traitor, the iuſt and honourable proceedings of her Maieſtie, and the honeſt and loyall endcuours of her Miniſters imployed in the diſcoucring of the treaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is true and not denied by himſelfe, that he was at Spawe about the time by him mencioned, and had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with Ienney in that place, and with Sir <hi>Francis Englefield</hi> in Flaunders, and that he hath written letters
<pb facs="tcp:23559:8"/>to. Sir <hi>Frauncis,</hi> and receiued letters from him: for if he ſhould denie the ſame, he were to be conuinced by good proofe: for it hath bin noted in him by many of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men Engliſh ſubiects, that both in thoſe partes and in Fraunce, hee did continually aſſociate him ſelfe with Engliſh Rebels and Fugitiues, If then you conſider with whom he hath conuerſed beyond the ſeas, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his religion with theirs, you wil iudge of his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation accordingly: and it is to be ſuppoſed, that thoſe men, knowen to be continuall practiſers againſt: the Queenes Maieſtie and this Realme, from whence for their Treaſons and vnnaturall demeanures they are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily baniſhed, will not in their conuenticles and meetings forget to bethinke them of their baniſhment, and howe they might be reſtored to their countrey, whereunto no deſert in her Maieſties life time (which God long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue) can wel (without her Maieſties great mercie) reſtore them. Then I pray you what conferences might <hi>M. Throckemorton</hi> haue with Sir <hi>Francis Englefield,</hi> with <hi>Ienney,</hi> with <hi>Liggons,</hi> with <hi>Owen,</hi> and with ſuch like, who were his daily companions in Fraunce and in the Iowe, countreis? He hath written letters to Sir <hi>Frauncis Engle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field:</hi> to what purpoſes? he haunted continually two Ambaſſadors in London, by whoſe meanes he ſent and receiued letters to and from beyond the ſeas daily. To whom, and from whom? euen to and from <hi>Thomas Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Throckemorton</hi> at Paris, men knowen to her Maieſtie and her Counſell, to be notorious practiſers, very inward with the Duke of Guyſe, and contriuers of the Treaſons and deuiſes for the inuaſion intended: and for very certaine knowledge thereof, we neede not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to <hi>Frauncis Throckemorton</hi> onely, (although he hath ſaid much of them) but to others of better credite then himſelfe.</p>
            <p>That the Duke of Guyſe did vndertake the enterpriſe to inuade the Realme with a forraine power, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed
<pb facs="tcp:23559:8"/>by the Pope and King of Spaine (a part of <hi>M. Throckemortons</hi> confeſſion) and he in trueth the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerer thereof to her Maieſtie: if he will ſay that it was but inuention, it will approue falſe. For ſithens he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the ſame, there haue bene diuers aducrtiſements thereof ſent to her Maieſtie from forraine Princes her Highneſſe louing neighbours and Allies, as alſo by other good meanes and intelligences from her Ambaſſadours and ſeruants reſiding in other Countries.</p>
            <p>If he denie (as he hath done) that he neuer had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any ſuch matter when he confeſſed the ſame, it hath no likelihood of trueth for <hi>Throckmorton</hi> was neuer knowen to be a Prophet to foretell things <hi>de futuro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He reſorted often to the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour, at the leaſt twice in a weeke when he was in London: this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repayre could not be to conferre with the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour for the exchange of money for his brother, as he pretended at his arraignement: there was ſome other cauſe. When he was apprehended, he had a Caſket coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with greene veluet, very cunningly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueied out of his chamber by a maide ſeruant of the houſe, taken vp vnder a beds ſide in his chamber (one of the gentlemen who were ſent to apprehend him then being in the chamber and vnknowing thereof) which Caſket not long after his apprehenſion, was by one <hi>Iohn Meredith</hi> a follower of <hi>Frauncis Throckemorton,</hi> conueyed to the handes of the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour: and why to him? If the matters therein might well haue abidden the light, why ſhoulde not the Caſket haue bene kept ſtill at home? and if not there, why not ſent to ſome other place of ſafetie, as well as to the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour? It is to be conceiued, that this Caſket was not conueyed thither without the direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Frauncis Throckmorton,</hi> though caried by <hi>Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith,</hi> who did well knowe of what moment the matters were that were within the Caſket, and of what danger to <hi>Throckemorton</hi> if they had bene diſcloſed, and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:23559:9"/>meant to beſtowe them in a ſafe place where they could not readily be had (as he thought) and with a perſon not vnacquainted with the qualitie of them. After the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Caſket, <hi>Meredith</hi> fledde: for in trueth he was priuie to the ſreaſons, and a fellowe practiſer in them: to whom <hi>Frauncis Throckemorton;</hi> being taken ſhort at the time of his apprehenſion, and forced to runne vp a ſtaire to deface a letter which he was then in writing to the Scottiſh Queene in Cipher (as he hath confeſſed) being ſuddenly apprehended, and ſo forced to depart away pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently out of his houſe, deliuered priuily into the hands of <hi>Meredith,</hi> either the Cipher by the which he was writing his letter to the Scottiſh Queene, or a letter in Cipher by him written vnto her: therefore he truſted <hi>Meredith</hi> as a than priuie to his doings. You are alſo to vnderſtande, that <hi>Throckemorton</hi> was in very great feare of the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of this Caſket after his apprehenſion: for remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning two or three daies priſoner in the houſe of one of the gentlemen that were ſent to apprehend him, before he was committed to the Towre, he was permitted to talke with a Sollicitor of his Lawe cauſe, who brought him cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine bookes drawen, or other like papers written, which hee made ſhowe to peruſe, but that was not the matter why he ſent for his Sollicitor: for in peruſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bookes, he conueyed into them a litle piece of paper, vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he had written w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>a cole, <hi>I would faine knowe whither my Caſket be ſafe,</hi> or to the like effect. The Sollicitor depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from him, and reſorting to <hi>Throckemortons</hi> houſe not farre diſtant from the place where he remained pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, opening his papers, did ſhake out this piece of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which he tooke vp and deliuered to one of <hi>Frauncis Throckemortons</hi> men, but the Casket was alreadie conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour: whereby you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celue what care he had of the Caſket, and howe much it might import him to haue the writings or matters within the ſame coucealed. He being examined touching the
<pb facs="tcp:23559:9"/>Casket, and what was in the ſame, he denied at the firſt, that euer he had any ſuch Casket, but finding afterwards that the Casket was diſcouered, he confeſſed the Casket, and ſaide there were certaine letters therein that came to his hands for the Scottiſh Queene from <hi>Thomas Morgan</hi> at Paris, and other letters and Papers, but conſelled not all, as it is ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Charles Page<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> came ouer into the Realme to euil purpoſea, as <hi>Throckemorton</hi> doth declare in his confeſsion, could not be inuented: for euen at the ſame time that he mentioneth. <hi>Paget</hi> came ouer, in ſecrete and ſuſpitious maner ſtaied not aboue xv dayes, indeuoured in a ſort to finde the diſpoſition of <hi>William Shallen</hi> Eſquier, how hee might ſtand, affected to giue aſsiſtance to the treaſons, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Paget</hi> diſcouered not directly his traiterous intets to <hi>Shelley:</hi> therefore all <hi>Throckemortons</hi> confeſsions were not forged or inuented.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the two papers produced at his arraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, containing the deſcription of the Hauens for the commodious landing of forces, do moſt apparantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demue him, &amp; are a manifeſt argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his priuity to the whole treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you may not forget y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he acknowledged one of the papers written in the Secretarie hand, to haue bene of his owne doing, but denyed the other written in the Romane hande: In the which vnder the title of Cheſhire &amp;c. is ſaid, <hi>Vpon the landing of forraine Supplies, Cheſter ſhal be taken:</hi> but what in your opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s might be vnderſtoode by that ſentence, <hi>Cheſter ſhalbe taken,</hi> when you ſhal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paper in Secretarie hand with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Romanc hande, intituled, <hi>The Names of Noblemen and gentlemen in euery Countie fitte to bee dealt withall in this matter.</hi> (which in trueth were both one, although the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane were ſomewhat more inlarged.) The queſtion is to bee aſked, <hi>What matter?</hi> The anſwere followeth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie, <hi>To aſſist the forraine forces that ſhall come to inuade the Realme:</hi> for that there is an other title in that paper
<pb facs="tcp:23559:10"/>ouer the names of the hauens, &amp;c. <hi>Hauens in euery coaſt fitte for the ſanding of forces.</hi> Now iudge you, to what end theſe names of men and deſcriptions of Hauens, their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, <hi>Capacities,</hi> what windes bring vnto them from Spaine, France and Flanders, were written and ſet downe by <hi>Throckemorton,</hi> the papers are both of his owne hand writing, and the Secretarie but a proiect or copie of the Romane.</p>
            <p>Is it not likely thinke you, that he would acquaint the Spanith Ambaſſadour with theſe papers (as he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed) when he made him partaker of the reſt of his trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous practiſes &amp; deui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es is you haue heard, &amp; thought his Caſket of treaſons to be moſt ſafely committed to his hands. It may bee thought that there is no man of ſo ſimple vnderſtanding, that will iudge to the contrarie, vnleſſe he be partially affected to excuſe the treaſons.</p>
            <p>And now to ſhew vnto you what mynd this man hath carried towards her Maieſtie, you are to be informed that <hi>Francis Throckemorton,</hi> after he had diſcouered to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie his courſe of practiſing, repenting himſelfe of his plaine dealing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bewraying thereof, ſayd to ſome of the Commiſſioners vpon occaſion of ſpeach, <hi>I woulde I had bene hanged when I firſt opened my month to declare any of the matters by me confeſſed.</hi> And being at other times ſent vnto by her Maieſtie with offer of pardon, if he would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the whole packe and complices of the treaſons, hee vſed this argument to perſwade her Maieſtie that he had confeſſed all, ſaying that ſithens hee had alreadie brought himſelfe by his confeſsions within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> danger of the lawes, to the vtter ruyne of his houſe and familie, hee wondered why there ſhould be any conceite in her Maieſtie, that he had not declared all. But to perſwade ſuch as were ſent vnto him for theſe purpoſes, the rather to beleeue that hee could diſcouer no more, at one time hee vied theſe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches following with great vehemencie: <hi>Nowe I haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed the ſecrets of her who was the decreſt thing vnto me in
<pb facs="tcp:23559:10"/>the worlde</hi> (meaning the Scottiſh Queene) <hi>and whome I thought no torment should haue drawen me ſo much to haue preiudiced as I have done by my confeſſions, I ſee no cauſe why, I ſhould ſpare any one, if I could ſay ought againſt him &amp; ſub. I haue failed of my faith towards her, I care not if I were han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> And when hee began firſt to confeſſe his treaſons, which hee did moſt vnwillingly, after hee was entred into the declaration of them, before al the Commiſſioners vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aduiſement, hee deſired hee might deliuer his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge but to one of them onely, whereunto they yeelded, and thereupon remouing aſule from the place where hee ſate by the Racke hee vſed this prouerbe in Italian, <hi>Chia perſo la fede a perſo l'honore,</hi> that is. He that hath falſed his faith, hath loſt his reputation: Meaning thereby (as it may be conceiued) that he had giuen his faith to bee a Traitor, and not to reueile the treaſons, and then began to confeſſe as you haue heard.</p>
            <p>By this diſcourſe, contayning the principal heads of his treaſons, and the proofes &amp; circumſtances of the ſame, you that are not tranſported with vndutifull myndes &amp; affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, will cleerely perceiue bowe impudently and vntrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he denyed at his arraignement the trueth of his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, charging her Maieſtie with crueltie, &amp; her miniſters with vntruethes in their proceeding againſt him.</p>
            <p>But the cauſe that moued him thereunto, was a vaine conceito he had taken, that his caſe was cleerein lawe by the intermiſsion of the time betwene his confeſsion made &amp; his arraigneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, grounding him ſelfe vpon a Statute of the 13, yere of her Maieſties Reigne, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which there are certaine treaſons ſpecified &amp; made of that nature, that no perſon ſhalbe arraigned for any of thoſe offences comitted within anie of the Queeues Maieſties dominious, vnleſſe the offendor be thereof indicted within ſixe moneths next after the ſame offence committed, &amp; ſhal not be arraigned for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, vnleſſe the offence be proued by the teſtimonie and othe of two ſufficient witneſſes, or his voluntarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion
<pb facs="tcp:23559:11"/>without violence: wherein he was greatly decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: For it was made manifeſt vnto him by the L. chiefe Iuſtice &amp; other of the iudges in Commiſsion at his trial, that his treaſons were puniſhable by a Statute of xxv. Edw. 3. which admitted no ſuch limitation of time or proofe.</p>
            <p>Herein his ſkin failed him, and forgot the aduiee giuen vnto him by ſome of the Commiſſioners, who (pitying his miſfortune for ſundrie good gifts of the minde appearing in him) aſſured him that there was no way ſo readie for him to redeeme his life, as by ſubmiſsion and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of his offence, which for a time after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his treaſons, he was contented to followe, and now eftſoones after his condemnation by a new ſubmiſsion to the Queenes Maieſtie the fourth of fune hath reſumed, that courſe. The ſubmiſsion <hi>verbatim</hi> written with his owne hand, followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To her moſt excellent Maieſtie, euen to her <hi>owne Royall handes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MOſt excellent Prince, and my moſt gratious Soueraigne, ſith to mee the most miſerable of all your Maiesties poore diſtreſſed ſubiects, being iuſtly condemned by the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and orderly courſe of your Maieſties Lawes, there reſteth no further meane of defence but ſubmiſſion: vonchſafe, moſt excellent Prince, graciouſly to accept the ſame, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in all hunmilitie, I here preſent vnto the hands of your moſt excellent Maieſtie, be ſeeching the ſame, that as Iuſtice bath bene deriued from your highneſſe, as from the fountaine, to the triall of mine actions: ſo I may receine from the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſome droppe of grace and mercie for the great &amp; grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offence where of I reſt by your Maieſties Lawes iuſtly condemned: ſome part, I ſay, of that your accuſtomed grations elemencie, whereof moſt your diſtreſſed ſubiects haue raſted, &amp; few bene depriued. And albeit the inconſiderate raſhneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:23559:11"/>vnbridled youth hath withdrawen me from that loyall reſpect, which nature and duetie bounde me to owe vnto your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, as to my lawfull and naturall dread ſoueraigne, and that the naturall care in me of the defence of my life mooned mee lately to the vntrue and vnduetifull gainſaying of ſome ſuch pointes as had bene before by me in moſt humble ſorte confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: neuertheles, I moſt humblie beſeech your moſt excellent Maieſtie, that in imitation of God, whoſe image (both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the happie place you holde, as alſo in regarde of your ſingular wiſedome and other the rare and ſingular vertues &amp; perfections wherewith God and nature hath plentifully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed you) you repreſent vnto vs here in earth, it may pleaſe your Maieſtie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſerate the lamentable eſtate of me now the moſt miſerable of all your Maieſties ſubiectes, and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſty to graunt vnto me remiſſion and forgiuenes, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe most humblie confeſſe my ſelfe worthie of death, but alſo in ſhewe of my repentance and ſorowfull afflicted minde, doe not craue at your Maiesties handes the prolonging of my life, if the ſame ſhall not ſtande with your gratious good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but rather deſire the trebling of the torment iuſtly by your Maieſties lawes impoſed vpon mee, of the ſame may bee any ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your Maieſtie for the haynous cryme wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I remaine by your Maieſties lawes iuſtly condemned, or any mitigation of your Maieſties indignation worthily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued againſt me, that deſire not to liue without your fauour, and dying will wiſh from my heart, that my ende may bee the beginning of your Maieſties ſecuritie, and my death the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of your life, and the increaſe both to your Maieſtie, and to this your most flouriſhing common wealth, of all the most happie bleſſings of almightie God.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Maieſties moſt wofull ſubiect in that he hath offended you.</hi> Francis Throckemorton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:23559:12"/>
            <p>HE ſent vnto her Maieſtie together with the ſayd ſubmiſsion, a declaration written likewiſe with his owne hand, contayning the effects of the moſt principall pointes of his treaſons formerly confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: retracting onely the accuſation of his father, and ſome other particularities of no moment to cleare him of his treaſons, the effect whereof followeth in his owne words, as he ſet them downe.<note place="margin">The decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note>
            </p>
            <p>THe onely cauſe why I coyned the practiſe firſt by me confeſſed, &amp; vniuſtly touched my father, was, for that partly I conceiued that the paper written ſo long ſithens, could not now by lawe haue touched me: but principally, for that I was willing thereby to colour the ſetting downe of thoſe names and hauens in Romane hand, which were written long after the time by me confeſſed vpon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of conference betweene the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour and me of this later practiſe.</p>
            <p>Mine intelligence with the Scortiſh Queene began a little before Chriſtmas was two yeres: the Cipher I had from <hi>Thomas Morgan</hi> in Fraunce: the firſt letter I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by <hi>Godfray Fulgeam,</hi> by whom alſo came all ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as I after receiued for the moſt part, vnleſſe it were ſuch as came to me by <hi>F. A.</hi> his hands, who as hee tolde mee,<note place="margin">William Ardington.</note> receiued them of the fellowe by me ſpoken of in my former confeſsions, whoſe name, I proteſt before God, I knowe not, nor whence he is. And for ſuch letters as came vnto mee in the abſence of <hi>Fulgeam,</hi> they were incloſed vnder a couerture from <hi>Fulgeam,</hi> &amp; were deliuered me by the hands of <hi>Robert Tunſtead</hi> his brother in Law, to whom I deliuered ſuch as I had for the Scottiſh Queene, couered with a directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Fulgeam,</hi> and once I remember or twiſe I ſent by one of my men called Butler, letters for the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Queene to the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Tunſtead,</hi> neere Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, couered with a direction to <hi>Tunſtead,</hi> and vnder a letter to <hi>Fulgea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> In ſuch letters as came to me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Q. were incloſed letters to <hi>F. A.</hi> many times, &amp; moſt
<pb facs="tcp:23559:12"/>times ſome for <hi>Thomas Morgan.</hi> Her letters to mee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, &amp;c. But before I retourned mine anſwere to her, I vnderſtoode of the death of the <hi>Duke of Lenox,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all heard from <hi>Morgan,</hi> with whom all mine intelligence was (for with my brother I neuer had any, other then that the matters by mee written to <hi>Morgan,</hi> were by him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to my brother moſt times) that by the perſwaſion of the Pope and the King of Spaine, the <hi>Duke of Guyſe</hi> had yeelded to performe the iourney in perſon: and that it was thought that the next way to attayne libertie for the Scottiſh Queene, and to reforme Scotlande, was to begin here in England; and therefore he deſired to knowe from me, whether in mine opinior. Catholiques woulde not backe any ſuch force as ſhould be ſent, conſidering a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of tolerance in religion for them, ſhould inſue the wel performing of the ſaid enterpriſe, and what I thought the force would amount vnto, both of horſe and foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and where I thought to be the fitteſt landing. Mine anſwere was, that as then, I ſawe no great probabilitie of the good ſucceſſe of ſuch an enterpriſe, for that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques were timorous, diſperſed, the matter perilous to be communicated to many, without which I ſaw not how any eſtimate could be made of the forces: beſides, that it was an eminent danger to the Scottiſh Queene, whereof I ſawe no remedie.</p>
            <p>I tooke notice of this matter in my next letters to the Scottiſh Queene, whoſe anſwere was, that ſhee lately heard of that determination, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Vpon my former anſwere to <hi>Morgan,</hi> he deſired me, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I would conferre with the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhould bee recommended from thence: hereupon the ſaid Ambaſſadour ſent for me, and brake with me in this matter, aſſuring me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in his opinion he found it verie caſie to make great alteration here with very little force, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the diſuſe in men to warre, and troubles woulde ſo amaſe them (as he thought) that they woulde be aſſoone
<pb facs="tcp:23559:13"/>ouerthrowen as aſſailed, and he could not thinke but in ſuch a caſe Catholikes would ſhewe themſelues, ſith the purpoſe tended to the obteyning for them libertie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and therefore hee deſired mee to acquaint him, what I thought men would doe in ſuch a caſe, and where I thought the fitteſt landing, and what holdes in theſe partes were eaſieſt to be ſurpriſed.</p>
            <p>I anſwered him, that as it ſeemed, the enterpriſe ſtood vpon great incertainties, if it depended of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a certaine force to be found here, which no man could aſſure him of, vnleſſe he had ſounded all the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, which was not poſsible without manifeſt hazarde of the diſcouerie of the purpoſe: for as for any great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, I know no one to be drawen into this action, that could carie any more then his ordinarie retinew: the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way in ſuch a caſe was (I tolde him) for ſuch as woulde bee drawen into this matter, and were of credite in their countreys, to leuie forces vnder colour of the Princes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</p>
            <p>But for that theſe things depended vpon vncertaine groundes, which was not fit to be uſed in ſo great an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſaid it was to be reſolued, that the force to bee ſent ſhould be of that number, that what backing ſoeuer they ſhould finde here, they might be able of themſelues to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with any force that might be prouided to be ſent againſt them, and therefore they could not bee leſſe then 15000. men. For the place of their landing, I ſaid it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended much vpon the force that ſhould be ſent: for if that were in great number, it mattered not where they landed: if in a ſmall companie, then was it requiſite that it ſhoulde be in the Countreys beſt affected, and furtheſt from her Maieſties principall forces, which I ſaid to be in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren parts on either ſide.</p>
            <p>To the danger of the Scottiſh Queene by me obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he ſaid he knewe no remedie, vnleſſe ſhe might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by ſome 200. horſe, which I tolde him I ſawe
<pb facs="tcp:23559:13"/>not to be poſsible, for that I knewe not any gentleman in thoſe partes (which were men, if any, to perfourme it) that I durſt wiſh to bee made acquainted with the matter before hande.</p>
            <p>Finally, our concluſion was, that I ſhould informe him of the Hauens as particularly as I could: and within fewe dayes after, finding by him that the force intended hither, was farre inferiour to that I ſpake of, and that there was ſome different betweene the Pope and the king of Spaine for the charge, I tolde him that the ſureſt courſe and of leaſt danger were, to ſend a ſupplie into Scotland, where a ſmall force would breede a great alteration, and things being there eſtabliſhed by the good liking of the king, I thought it was in him by a continuall warre, and by incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſo to anoy this ſtate, as her Maieſtie here ſhoulde be forced to yeelde the libertie of the Scottiſh Queene, and what ſhould thereupon haue bene reaſonably demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the benefite of Catholikes here. And herein I ſaid it would be a great furtherance, if at the ſame time ſome fewe were landed in Irelande, where, although they abid the ſame hazarde that the former forces ſuſtained, yet would the charge be ſo great to her Maieſtie, and ſo great an occaſion of diſperſing of her forces, as a much leſſe companie then was ſpoken of firſt by me, would (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing landed here in a conuenient place) ſhake the mindes of men generally, and be of force (if any thing) to drawe them to ſhewe themſelues, in the furtherance of the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>He vtterly reiected the purpoſe for Ireland, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked not the purpoſe for Scotlande: but ſtill hee was in minde to haue forces landed here, and therefore deſired me verie earneſtly to inquire particularly of the Haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s on the ſide of Cumberland and Lancaſhire, and what men were dwelling there that were well affected in religion, and what places eaſie to be taken, and what apt for forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23559:14"/>
            <p>The next time that I went to the Spaniſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, he found himſelfe a grieued that he vnderſtood mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were determined in France without his priuitie: and told me that <hi>Parſons</hi> the Ieſuite was gone to Rome, ſent as he thought, to vnderſtand the Popes minde.</p>
            <p>Soone after came ouer my brother <hi>Thomas,</hi> to make an ende of our accompt, and to perſwade me to come ouer, aſſuring mee that for ought he could ſee in likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the enterpriſe was neuer like to take effect. In the time of his being heere; and while I entertained intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence with the Scottiſh Queene concerning her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour ſent for me, and tolde me of the comming ouer of <hi>Mope</hi> to view Suſſex and the Hauens, and as he thought, to taſte the beſt of acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt there: whereat he ſeemed to bee agrieued, for that ſuch matters had not bene left to him, beeing one that they in France made beleeue that they relyed vpon principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this enterpriſe. Afterwardes, the Ambaſſadour tolde me, that it was <hi>Charles Paget,</hi> and that he was returned, but where he had bene hee knewe not, and at the ſame time I receiued a letter from <hi>Morgan,</hi> that it was <hi>Paget:</hi> but aſſuring me, and ſo willed me to aſſure the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, that his comming was not to moue any man, but onely to viewe the countrey, for that the moouing of any man was referred to him. I did ſo: and he intreated me to remember him for thoſe foreſaide names and Hauens, ſaying that ſo it were done exactly by the Spring, it would ſuffice: for that ſooner he ſaw no likeliehoode of the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>My brother hauing made an ende of his accompt with me, retourned with this reſolution betweene vs, (I proteſt before God,) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if the enterpriſe ſucceeded not betweene this and the next Spring nowe paſt, that I woulde fettle my things here and goe ouer. And for this cauſe, he being gone, I went downe into the countrey, both to fell and take order for my land in thoſe partes, as alſo to ſetch the
<pb facs="tcp:23559:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>draught of Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Hauens for the moſt part of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, which had bene ſet downe by me aboue two yeres ſince, and left behinde me at Feckenham in my Studie.</p>
            <p>Not finding the draught at Feckenham, I returned to London, where I founde the note of names in Secretarie hande, which I caried to the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour, and there drewe that other in Romane hande in his Studie, putting downe <hi>Cheſter</hi> to be taken, in reſpect of the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineſſe as I thought, &amp; the rather to giue him incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the matter. I left it with him, promiſing him that by the next ſpring I woulde perfect it, if I taried ſo long, making knowen vnto him, that I was had in ſuſpition, &amp; my determination to be gone: but he preſſed the contrarie of me, aſſuring me, that if the enterpriſe proceeded not, he would then alſo depart.</p>
            <p>Whether Sir <hi>Frauncis Englefielde</hi> were a dealer in this practiſe or no, I know not: but ſure I am (for ſo the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour tolde me) that Sir <hi>Frauncis</hi> had intelligence with the ſaid Ambaſſadour all the time of his being here.</p>
            <p>The Spaniſh Ambaſſadour tolde me that he heard the people of Northwales were generallie wel affected, and therefore he deſired to haue the hauens of that countrie: I tolde him that hereafter I would helpe him thereunto, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though no good might be expected there, for the reaſons by me ſet downe in my firſt confeſſion; and hereupon the day before mine apprehenſion, the Ambaſſadour ſent me backe the ſaid paper in Romane hand, deſiring me to ſet downe the ſame at my leaſure more exactly, which was the cauſe that it was not in my greene veluet Casket. The writings in my Casket were ſireh as were by mee confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and came vnto my hands as I haue confeſſed.</p>
            <p>I Moſt humbly beſeeche her moſt excellent Maieſtie, that the extremitie which I haue alreadie ſuſtained, and the cauſes by me diſcouered, to the ſafetie of her Maieſtie and the ſtate, not made knowen (as hath appeared) by any other meane then by my ſelfe, may craue at her handes,
<pb facs="tcp:23559:15"/>the extending of her gratious commiſeration towardes the relieuing of the lamentable eſtate of me, her Maieſties poore diſtreſſed ſubiect, &amp; mine, if God for mine offences forbid not the ſame.</p>
            <p>Nowe iudge all yee, that be not peruerſly affected, whether <hi>Throckemorton</hi> be iuſtly condemned, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his confeſſions (though as hee pretended, extorted from him by violence) be of force in Lawe againſt him: he hath conſpired to ouerthrowe the ſtate: to bring in ſtrangers to inuade the Realme: to remoue her Maieſtie from her lawfull and naturall right and inheritance to the Crowne of England, and to place a ſtranger in her ſeate: but this laſt point, for placing of a ſtranger, will (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce) be denyed: then note, that in the whole courſe of the practiſe, the greateſt barre to the proſecution of the enterpriſe, was, they found no way how to put the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Queene in ſafetie. Then, if theſe dangerous treaſons be diſcouered by torture, (the onely meanes left vnto Princes to diſcouer treaſons and attemptes againſt their States and Perſons, where they finde apparant matter to induce ſuſpition, as in the caſe of <hi>Throckemorton,</hi> vpon ſight of the plottes of hauens &amp;c.) may the Law touch the traitour or not? If any man holde this queſtion negatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hold him for a friend to traitours and treaſons, and an enemie to the Queenes Maieſtie, whome God long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and confound her enemies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
